Guide to the Anna Schwartz Papers, 1929-2012 RL.01152
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Shadow Open Market Committee, 1998-2006, 1 box
  - 1-2 May 2005 meeting (Box 11)
  - 4-5 December 2005 meeting (Box 11)
  - 7-8 May 2006 meeting (Box 11)
  - Charles Plosser, "Monetary Policy: A Shadow Perspective," 2002 (Box 11)
- Milton Friedman Materials, 1952-2008, 3 boxes
  This series covers Schwartz's longstanding collaboration with Nobel Prize-winning economist Milton Friedman of the University of Chicago. It is divided into three subseries: Writings, Writings About Milton Friedman, and Correspondence. The Writings subseries contains Friedman's columns for Newsweek and the Wall Street Journal along with other journalistic pieces; privately circulated memorandums; talks and articles from throughout his career, including drafts; and materials relating to four major projects: A Monetary History of the United States, 1867-1960, Monetary Trends in the United States and the United Kingdom, and "Monetary Statistics of the United States," all co-authored with Schwartz, and The Essence of Friedman, a collection of previously published essays. The Writings About Milton Friedman subseries includes both journalistic clippings and academic articles and is arranged chronologically, with separate folders devoted to interviews, the 1976 Nobel, and obituaries/memorials. The Correspondence subseries mostly contains Friedman's extensive correspondence with Schwartz concerning their collaborations in the 1960s and 1970s, although it also includes letters to and from other colleagues. It is arranged chronologically with the exception of a few subject-specific files. Correspondence not directly concerning Milton Friedman is filed in the general "Correspondence" series.
  - Writings
    - Memorandums, 1965-1986 (Box 11)
    - Newsweek articles, 1966-1986, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Wall Street Journal articles, 1974-1998 (Box 11)
    - Journalism, 1973-1989 and undated (Box 11)
    - Articles listed in AEA Index of Economic Journals (Box 11)
    - Articles and Talks, 1952-1998 and undated
      - Classical Counterrevolution in Monetary Theory and Policy, 1952 (Box 11)
      - Why the American Economy is Depression-Proof, 1954 (Box 11)
      - A Statistical Illusion in Judging Keynesian Models, 1957 (Box 11)
      - Permanent Income Hypothesis, 1958 (Box 11)
      - Foreign Economic Aid, 1958 (Box 11)
      - Consumption and Saving; "Horizon" in the Permanent Income Hypothesis, 1959 (Box 11)
      - The Demand for Money: Some Theoretical and Empirical Results, 1959 (Box 11)
      - Judging the Predictive Abilities of the Quantity and Income Expenditure Theories, 1959 (Box 11)
      - The Demand for Money, 1961-1962 (Box 11)
      - The Lag in Effect of Monetary Policy, 1961 (Box 11)
      - The Report of the Commission on Money and Credit: An Essay in Petitio Principii, 1961 (Box 11)
      - Should there be an Independent Monetary Authority?, 1962 (Box 11)
      - Statement at Hearings of Banking and Currency Commission, House of Representatives, 1964 (Box 11)
      - Henry Simons Lecture, University of Chicago: The Monetary Theory and Policy of Henry Simons, 1967 (Box 11)
      - The Role of Monetary Policy: AEA Presidential Address, 1967 (Box 11)
      - International Encyclopedia of Social Sciences entries, 1968 (Box 11)
      - Fiscal and Monetary Policy talk in Geneva at Bache Institute, 1969 (Box 11)
      - Euro-Dollar Market: Some First Principles, 1969 (Box 11)
      - Controls on Interest Rates Paid by Banks, 1970 (Box 11)
      - A Theoretical Framework for Monetary Analysis, 1970 (Box 11)
      - A Quantity Theory of Money, 1970 (Box 11)
      - "Money" for Encyclopedia Britannica, 1970 (Box 11)
      - Irresponsible Monetary Policy, 1971 (Box 11)
      - "Monetary Policy" draft for symposium of American Philosophical Society, 1971 (Box 11)
      - Monetary Aggregates and Monetary Policy, 1971 (Box 11)
      - Statement for Joint Economic Committee hearing "How Well are Fluctuating Exchange Rates Working?" 1973 (Box 11)
      - Inflation and Unemployment, 1976 (Box 11)
      - Nobel Banquet response, 1976 (Box 11)
      - Adam Smith's Relevance for 1976 (Box 11)
      - Prices of Money and Goods Across Frontiers: the Pound and Dollar over a Century, 1980 (Box 11)
      - Monetary Policy: Theory and Practice, JMCB lecture and article, 1981-1982 (Box 11)
      - Monetary Society for a Free Society, 1981 (Box 11)
      - What Could Reasonably Have Been Expected from Monetarism: the U.S., 1983 (Box 11)
      - Lessons from the 1979-1982 Monetary Policy Experiment, 1984 (Box 11)
      - Comment on Leland Yeager's Paper on the Keynesian Heritage, 1984 (Box 11)
      - Tribute to Arthur Burns, 1987 (Box 12)
      - The Political Clout of the Elderly, 1988 (Box 12)
      - Merits of Flexible Exchange Rates anthology, 1988 (Box 12)
      - Exchange Rate in a Fiat Money World, 1988 (Box 12)
      - John Maynard Keynes: Working Papers in Economics, 1988 (Box 12)
      - Using the Market for Social Development, 1989 (Box 12)
      - Fraser Forum, 1989 (Box 12)
      - Views on the State of Affairs, 1989 (Box 12)
      - The Adam Smith Address: Suicidal Impulse of the Business Community, 1990 (Box 12)
      - Why Government is the Problem, 1991 (Box 12)
      - Speaking to Oppenheimer Clients, 1991-1992 (Box 12)
      - Economic Freedom, Human Freedom, Political Freedom, 1991 (Box 12)
      - Churning Your Money at the Friendly Fed, 1993 (Box 12)
      - "Plucking Model" of Business Fluctuations Revisited, 1993 (Box 12)
      - The Euro, 1997 (Box 12)
      - If Only the U.S. was as Free as Hong Kong, 1998 (Box 12)
      - Britain: 1952-1954 (from Two Lucky People), undated (Box 12)
      - Tradeoffs in Monetary Policy, undated (Box 12)
    - Positive Economics reviews, 1954 (Box 12)
    - Monetary versus Fiscal Policy, with Walter Heller, 1969 (Box 12)
    - Monetary History of the United States, with Anna Schwartz, reviews and articles, 1964-2000 (Box 12)
    - Monetary History of the United States edits and corrections, 1964-1978 (Box 12)
    - CATO forum on Monetary History text, 2003 (Box 12)
    - Anti-Semitism, Banks, and the Great Depression, 1974 (Box 12)
    - Monetary Statistics of the United States reviews, 1969-1974 (Box 12)
    - Monetary Trends in the United States and United Kingdom reviews and corrections, 1982-1984 (Box 12)
    - Trends in Money, Income, and Prices - correspondence re: revisions, 1966-1967 (Box 12)
    - Essence of Freedom drafts, 4 folders (Box 12)
    - Silver Memorandum and the Crime of 1873, 1988 (Box 12)
    - Two Lucky People reviews, 1998 (Box 12)
    - The Great Contraction, 2008 edition, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - "Life on the Hook" Friedman autobiography (?), undated (Box 12)
    - Untitled and undated comments by Milton Friedman (Box 12)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, May 1956-July 1999, 5 folders (Box 12)
    - Correspondence between Friedman, Schwartz, and Meltzer re: Proxmire's letter to Burns, 1973-1974 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence with Joe Cobb re: Gold Coinage Act, 1981 (Box 13)
    - Correspondence with Schwartz, Hetzel, and A. Orphanides re: Orphanides' paper, "The Quest for Prosperity without Inflation," May-July 1999 (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 13)
  - Writings about Friedman (Box 13)
    - Clippings, 1968-2008 and undated (Box 13)
    - Interviews, 1973-2007 (Box 13)
    - Nobel Prize, 1976 (Box 13)
    - Rose Friedman, "Milton Friedman: Husband and Colleague," 1976-1977 (Box 13)
    - Bo Axell and Birgitta Swedenborg, "Milton Friedman och ekonomipriset," 1977 (Box 13)
    - Anna Schwartz, "Milton Friedman," 1979 (Box 13)
    - Alan Walters, "Milton Friedman," with correspondence, 1985 (Box 13)
    - Jonathan Peterson, "The Captain of Capitalism," 1986 (Box 13)
    - Robert Hetzel, "Development and Influence of the Ideas of Milton Friedman," 1997 (Box 13)
    - Pacific Research Institute, "Milton Friedman," 1997 (Box 13)
    - Deirdre McCloskey, "Milton," 2003 (Box 13)
    - Richard Timberlake, "Golden Facades," and correspondence, 2004 (Box 13)
    - Michel de Vroey, "On the Right Side for the Wrong Reason," 2004 (Box 13)
    - Costas Meghir, "A Retrospective on Friedman's Theory of Permanent Income," 2004 (Box 13)
    - John Ward, "The View from Up There," 2006 (Box 13)
    - Robert Hetzel, "The Contributions of Milton Friedman to Economics," 2006 (Box 13)
    - Obituaries and memorials, 2006-2007 (Box 13)
    - David Laidler's review of Lanny Ebenstein's Milton Friedman, 2007 (Box 13)
    - Edward Nelson, "Milton Friedman and U.S. Monetary History," 2007 (Box 13)
    - Anna Schwartz and Edward Nelson responses to Paul Krugman, 2007-2008 (Box 13)
    - Macesich, "Dictionary of the History of American Banking," undated (Box 13)
  - Xeroxed photographs of Friedman (Box 13)
  - Events and programs in Friedman's honor (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous unlabelled materials, undated (Box 13)
  - Conference in Honor of Milton Friedman's 60th Birthday: scrapbook pages with photographs (also listed above in Conferences Series) (Box 18)
- Writings by Others, 1932-2009, 5 boxes
  The Writings by Others series is arranged alphabetically by last name and contains both drafts and published pieces by Schwartz's colleagues and other notable figures. Several writers receive a significant amount of coverage: Michael Bordo, Charles Calomiris, Robert Hetzel, Edward Kane, Allan Meltzer, and Scott Sumner. The "Referee's Reports" subseries is devoted to Schwartz's editorial work providing reader's reports.
  - Abrams, Burton (Box 13)
  - Alvarez, Atkeson, Edmund (Box 13)
  - Ball, Lawrence (Box 13)
  - Benderly, Jason and Burton Zwick (Box 13)
  - Bernanke, Ben (Box 13)
  - Blair, Tony (Box 13)
  - Blinder, Alan (Box 13)
  - Bordo, Michael, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Brenner, Reuben and Gabrielle, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Brunner, Karl (Box 13)
  - Buiter, William (Box 13)
  - Cagan, Phillip (Box 13)
  - Calomiris, Charles, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Capie, Forrest (Box 13)
  - Cachetti, Genberg, Lipsky, Wadhwani (Box 13)
  - Collins, Michael (Box 13)
  - Demyanyk, Y., et al. (Box 13)
  - Dorn, James A. (Box 13)
  - Eggertsson, Gauti (Box 13)
  - Fand, David (Box 13)
  - Feldstein, Martin (Box 13)
  - Flandreau, Marc (Box 13)
  - Gandolfi, Gandolfi, and Barash (Box 13)
  - George, Eddie (Box 13)
  - Greenspan, Alan (Box 13)
  - Grilli, Enzo, and Maw Cheng Yang (Box 14)
  - Hanke, Steve (Box 14)
  - Hetzel, Robert, 10 folders (Box 14)
  - Humpage, Owen (Box 14)
  - Humphrey, Thomas (Box 14)
  - Irwin, Douglas (Box 14)
  - Kane, Edward, 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Kaufman, George (Box 14)
  - Kroos, Herman (essays in memorial) (Box 14)
  - Laidler, David (Box 14)
  - Lastrapes, William and George Selgin (Box 14)
  - Levin, Andrew and John Taylor (Box 14)
  - Lindbeck, Assar et al. (Box 14)
  - Mason, Joseph (Box 14)
  - McCallum, Bennett (Box 14)
  - Meltzer, Allan, 7 folders (Box 14)
  - Meltzer, Allan, 10 folders (Box 15)
  - Myers, Beckhart, Smith, and Brown (Box 15)
  - Neal, Larry and Daniel Barzebat (Box 15)
  - Nelson, Edward (Box 15)
  - Nishimura, Shizuya (Box 15)
  - Obstfeld, Maurice (Box 15)
  - Officer, Lawrence (Box 15)
  - Overturf, Steven (Box 15)
  - Reitz, Stefan and Mark Taylor (Box 15)
  - Rich, George (Box 15)
  - Reinhart, Carmen and Kenneth Rogoff (Box 15)
  - Sarno, Lucio, and Mark Taylor (Box 15)
  - Schneider, Erich (Box 15)
  - Schwartz, David (Box 15)
  - Schwartz, Joel (Box 15)
  - Selgin, George (Box 15)
  - Silver, Andrew (Box 15)
  - Summer, Scott, 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Taylor, James (Box 16)
  - Thornton, Daniel (Box 16)
  - Timberlake, Richard and Kevin David (Box 16)
  - Todd, Walker (Box 16)
  - Veronesi, Paul and L. Zingales (Box 16)
  - Warburton, Peter (Box 16)
  - Weber, E. Juerg (Box 16)
  - Weller, Christian and Jurgen von Hagan (Box 16)
  - Wood, Geoffrey (Box 17)
  - Untitled U.S. Exchange Rate paper, undated (Box 17)
  - Referee Reports
    - Burdekin, Richard: Nontraditional Monetary Policy Options, 2004-2005 (Box 17)
    - Frankel, Jeremy: A Proposed Monetary Regime for Small Commodity Exporters, 2002 (Box 17)
    - Hanes, Christopher: The Liquidity Trap and U.S. Interest Rates in the 1930s, 2003 (Box 17)
    - Hetzel, Robert (Box 17)
    - Rockoff, Hugh (Box 17)
    - Schnabel, Isabel: The Role of Liquidity and Implicit Guarantees in the German Twin Crisis of 1931, 2005 (Box 17)
    - Selgin, George and Lawrence White: Credible Currency, 2001 (Box 17)
    - Werner, Richard: The Historical Rationale of Credit Direction Policies, 2003 (Box 17)
    - White, Lawrence: Did Hayek and Robbins Deepen the Great Depression?, 2007 (Box 17)
    - Wood, John: Companies of Merchants, 2002-2003 (Box 17)
    - Extending the Friedman-Schwartz Monetary Base, the Balance of Payments, and U.S. Economic Performance by Period, 1789-1932, 2000 (no author) (Box 17)
    - Fixed Exchange Rates Under a Currency Board versus a Central Bank, 2004 (no author) (Box 17)
- Electronic Materials, 2012; 80 Megabytes; 353 files including mostly Word and PDF document files; approximately 80 megabytes.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Electronic records in this file have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.
  Scope and Contents
  This file includes electronic materials received from Schwartz's office at the National Bureau of Economic Research office in New York City. The electronic materials cover professional and personal papers of Anna Schwartz, including correspondence, conference files, research files, writing drafts, writings, newspaper clippings, photos, and her bio/CV.